Heat.
Hey, Heat.
Well, good morning everyone and welcome
to the Fiber Broadband Association's
Five for Breakfast. We're now in our
eighth episode of 2026. The gold sponsor
of Five for Breakfast is Conducts. So
after nearly five years, five, we are
starting to see the actual checks being
cut to service providers in Louisiana
with the NTI bead program. So
congratulations to Venith and Thomas and
the whole crew at the Louisiana
Broadband Office and all the state
broadband offices for all your efforts
to finally get the beat funding to the
finish line. It's exciting times. And
yesterday, the Fiber Broadband
Association hosted its annual public
policy summit and flyin in DC at the uh
AT&T Center right on Capitol Hill. And
today we're holding our DC flyin on the
hill. So our policy summit, we heard
from chairman Richard Hudson from North
Carolina. He's always a great advocate
for broadband. Uh the beat champion uh
Senator Shelley Bore Capo from West
Virginia. You know, West Virginia is
just amazing in their fiber um locations
with their bead program. Also, we heard
from FCC Commissioner Olivia Trustee,
broadband leader Cong Congresswoman uh
Jennifer Mlullen from Virginia, NTI
Chief of Staff Brooke Donalan, uh
Speaker Mike Johnson from Louisiana,
policy advisor Cyrus Artis, and um we
also had a great interesting talk from
chief uh Washington correspondent from
New York Times, Carl Hol. So, uh, really
great policy summit as always and
hopefully you guys can join us next
year. And last week on fire for
breakfast, our guest was Michael Thomas
from Network Connects who discussed the
hidden infrastructure behind AI and
hyperscaling our networks. Michael and
his team are currently all hunkered down
in Abalene, Texas where they are
deploying inline amplifier shelters.
That's so you get those about every 50
miles in these big fiber deployments uh
for the mass deployment of fiber for the
half a trillion dollar Stargate AI data
center project. So that's a a big
hyperscaler project down in well I think
it's the largest in the world. So
exciting things going on there. So if
you missed that session you can go to
our website and watch the replay. Today
on Fire for Breakfast, our guest is our
good friend Ernesto Falcon from the
California PUC to discuss broadband
competition and pricing strategies in
California's urban markets. Uh Ernesto
is the program manager for the
communications and broadband policy
branch of the public advocacies office
within the California Public Utilities
Commission. His team focused on
protecting customers of communications
company in California by analyzing and
recommending solutions in several areas
including improving service quality,
advancing broadband access and
affordability and participating in the
CPU and legislative proceedings to
address customer needs and challenges.
Uh Ernesto was the former senior
legislative counsel at the electronic uh
frontier foundation EFF with the primary
focus on intellectual property, open
internet issues, privacy, broadband
access, artificial intelligence and
competition policy. Uh he represent EFS
advocacy on behalf of its members and
consumers for free and open internet
before the state legislature and
congress. Prior to FF, Ernesto worked in
the United States House of
Representatives and for nonprofit public
knowledge in Washington DC. So, welcome
Ernie. It's great to have you here.
Haven't talked to you in a few months
now. Um, so great to catch up. And for
audience, please type in your questions
and go. We'll work those in discussions.
With that, I will turn it over to
Ernesto.
>> Hey Gary, thanks and thanks for for
having me and thanks for uh inviting me
here. Um, yeah, I'll give a bit of the
background of my what my team does at
the public advocates office, which is
kind of like a an agency within an
agency. We're part of the PUC, but we're
statutoily independent. We are uh we are
directed by a governor appointed Senate
confirmed uh director. So, um, separate
from the five commissioners. And, you
know, I do think of our mandate and our
work really is to think about how do we
bring down consumer prices? uh how do we
improve quality of service in the
communications infrastructure space uh
and public safety is is kind of near and
dear an important mission of the
commission. So we do a lot of work
particularly with the aid of all of fire
season and things of that nature. So in
this work what we did uh my one of my
senior researchers uh Bishia Yei uh
teamed up with the UN University of
California Santa Barbara uh to utilize
what's called the broadband query tool
and what that tool does is it it scans
in real time dynamic pricing just like
what is happening in the promotional
rates at an address level um we're able
to collect a fairly large sample of data
well into the multiple thousands
uh kind of spread throughout the state
uh to give us real statistically
relevant information here on what's
happening and what are the contours of
what we were looking at in terms of
competition in the urban markets. We
chose urban market specifically to kind
of set aside the question of you know is
it too rural or is it too expensive to
deploy or any of the you know
traditional cost barriers uh
particularly for highspeed internet you
know next generation networks and uh you
spread out our analysis in our our four
four major cities throughout the you
know throughout the state and this this
was a new study that builds off kind of
traditional work we've done and um one
of the sorry one sec One of the things
we do on an annual basis is Oh, hold on.
I believe it's one slide back here. Um,
okay. It seems to be skipping that slide
for some reason, but what we I'll I'll
kind of explain what we do on an annual
basis. We collect kind of consumer
pricing information large and see where
the trend lines are on um what
Californians are paying. You know, is it
going up? Is it going down? How do we
compare amongst the 50 states? uh in our
latest report we issued uh at the end of
last year, you know, found that
California was losing a bit of its
competitive edge on pricing. Uh some
states, a handful of states were
starting to get ahead of us in terms of
kind of average pricing, particularly,
you know, in the higher speeds.
>> And the the concern, you know, the the
next real mission for us is to to
dissect why and where and what can the
state do to respond. And so part of the
analysis within that analysis was
looking at these urban markets to see
what what is actually happening on
prices and why what are the kind of the
elements in the ground. And one thing
that was notable was um the fiber
broadband association had this study
showing that we were uh kind of fi you
know not necessarily fiber poor but not
ahead of the curve in terms of fiber
penetration meaning the number of
California customers who have access to
uh fiber to the home is is not on par
with with the rest of the country. And
so what does that mean in terms of
competition and where does where does
the source of competition happen? you
know, we were getting a lot of
assertions of fixed wireless broadband
making a serious impact in the market,
you know, so we look into that, testing
the whether that whether that's true and
to what extent that's true. Um, and my
background, I've I've done a lot of, you
know, infrastructure analysis and work
in the fiber space. And so figuring out
how to fix up where California is and
get us further along is is kind of a
near and dear project of my of mine, you
know, dating back many years. So
what we did find was
when the incumb the gigabit tier appears
to be where the center gravity of
competition and pricing is happening. Um
this is like a snapshot of the data but
let me I'll kind of summarize um some
key findings here. when a cable company
that's offering a gigabit service uh
when they're facing competition from
slower what we call sub gigabit options
uh fixed wireless broadband satellite
for example there is not a noticeable
change in their pricing structure uh
while there's data showing there's some
churn in terms of people leaving cable
for fixed wireless broadband uh the
reality is it does not appear that cable
really does much about their pricing
structure across the board however that
is not sure when there's at least one
alternative gigabit provider. And
traditionally that that tends to be a
fiber entity uh coming in. And so what
the data was showing us was when when
there is limited to no competition, even
with promotional pricing, it was it was
consistently higher across the board.
However, the moment there is a at least
a duopoly, you know, two two gigabit
options uh primarily driven by fiber,
that's when the pricing structure of the
existing, you know, gigabit and you
know, incumbent uh really starts to
change. You know, on average, we were
seeing prices go down anywhere between
$15 to $40 a month um in in the areas
where you're seeing at least two
options, even more so when there's
three. the Bay Area is um quite
competitive in terms of you know having
at least three options some places even
having four options
and so looking at the number of
residents who are you know essentially
lacking fiber and and that is kind of a
proxy for lacking uh 2 gigabit options
uh because traditionally cable has
already upgraded to docs 3.1 uh they're
rolling at doc 4.0 know in some places
now you know they're already kind of at
the gigabit level and above. Um this is
kind of the spread of the state in terms
of where the fiber entry would make a a
real difference in pricing. If if the
responsiveness of the pattern where
there's a second option at a gigabit or
higher level uh comes in primarily from
fiber entry. Our calculation is the
number of residents that would save
money. Kind of the total calculated
estimation is is well over a billion
dollars in consumer savings. You know,
driven by, you know, the reduction of
pricing as a means of retaining
retaining those customers by cable and
the, you know, promotional aggressive
first bid price of the new entrance
that's trying to acquire those
customers. So, for us, it's it's a
fairly significant amount of money that
would um you know, save customers from
competition. It also is likely a large
source of the drag in terms of
California falling uh a little further
behind in kind of competitive pricing.
Oh, and and this is the the broadband
pricing report I was mentioning earlier.
This is traditionally what we've done in
terms of analyzing lots of different
options, lots of different speed tiers
and kind of where the subscriber
population is located um and and kind of
the trends on pricing. And so as I
mentioned earlier, uh we know we were
seeing a a throughput line of our our
ranking and competition in terms of
compar comparison to the other 50 states
or the number of states that are
participating in territories that are
participating in these um the FCC's
urban rate survey. um you know we were
seeing the the the slippage of our of
our previous leadership in this space
and and kind of you know slight decline
and so as I mentioned earlier the
calculated savings this is generally how
you know using kind of the the FCC's
public data on you know g essentially
areas that have a single gigabit option
which carrier uh or cable company you
know exists in those areas it's it's
predominantly cable uh which indicates
it's not really uh there's not really a
set of of sole fiber fiber gigabit
entities out there. Uh it's primarily in
the cable space. And so this is how we
kind of came up with the calculation of
the total uh cost savings by you know
benchmarking an average of showing the
range of price decreasing that occurs
with the carriers when they face
competition. And we opted to average
across 300 500 gigabit for a couple
reasons. one the center of gravity of um
consumers at this point uh a a a
minority of people use 100 megabits or
or lower in terms of internet access. Uh
I would say today about 75% of
Californians subscribe to 300 or above
in terms of broadband. uh almost half
are are at 500 above which I think is
very important for policy makers to
recognize because we allow
you know how many 100 down 20 up options
are out there as a means of assessing
you know how healthy the market is or or
do we need to do more to promote
infrastructure and you know I I can say
with a pretty uh high degree of
confidence based on where subscribers
are and kind of where the consumer
demand is uh in the state at large the
the gra the center of gravity is is
right? You moving towards the gigabit
era. Um I think in a short handful of
years at this point just given the the
shift that continues to move upward with
consumer the consumer usage um what
people are buying in terms of what and
which I think reflects what they need
and and need often. Um, you know, we are
going to be at a point where the gigabit
is a pretty standard product that almost
everyone would like to have as like
their standard offering, which again, I
think explains why sub gigabit offerings
are not really forcing cable to rejigger
their prices or or respond. I think they
the industry knows that's where the
consumers are heading to and they're
well situated to capture the lion share
of of revenue in that respect. So yeah,
I mean that's that's essentially like
the the key findings of our study. Um,
you know, we're exploring ways that uh
promote more fiber uh deployment. One
example is uh we recently came out with
a joint agreement with AT&T on the
carrier blast resort proceeding. So this
is the legacy obligation to uh
universally serve voice. um the in
public local exchange carriers like they
you know AT&T bank our largest provider
in the state of California has often you
know referred to these you know legacy
obligations as a restraint on the
ability to deploy more fiber. Um my pro
position in in terms of working with
them to come up to an agreement to
present to the commission has been if if
if true and I and I think there was a
layer a layer of truth there. Well then
we need to have a structured mean of
transitioning as much of the copper
copper network over to fiber and have
some concrete means of of of
facilitating that transition. So you
know our hopes is um you know coler will
be you know the the evolution of colar
to kind of modernize broadband
regulation will facilitate accelerated
deployment of fiber which then delivers
lower cost you know lower cost offerings
to consumers and you know fulfills our
main mandate which is to bring down
prices. Um, so you know that that is
that is work that is beginning and and I
think we're going to continue to explore
other ways that we can help you know at
least get people to two options and in
some respects uh you know there there
will be a point where we can try and
think about how to get the third option
as well.
Well, Ernie, this is super interesting
and it kind of matches some of our
research. Um, you know, in our latest
study, um, attach rates. So, when you,
you know, you're when you have fiber
deploy, um, what we're seeing is that,
um, fiber providers get about 45%
uptake. Uh, you know, so most business
models are, you know, assume somewhere
between 25 and 40%. So right off the bat
they're able to beat their business
model with 45%. But what's really
interesting is that when you have more
than one fiber provider in a re in
location um take rates go from 45% to
61%.
Which shows that there's plenty of
business for more than one fiber
operator um in a community. And you know
further if I look at just like AT&T had
their earnings report looked amazing um
this quarter that um so what they say is
that not only when they deploy fiber are
they're they getting better uptake um
they're getting more average revenue per
user because they're be able to sell
more services like streaming services
and so forth. But also uh 42% of their
fiber subscribers are also subscribing
to their wireless. So they're mobile
wireless. So you have more ARPO, you
have lower cost from ARPO um from lower
opex and you're getting selling more
services, more attach rates, and you're
able to reduce the carbon footprint. So
it seems like winwinwinwin
for providers. And then also I I have to
note the the providers you have on here
are all benefiting from uh President
Trump's uh tax benefits that he had in
the one big beautiful bill that he had
100% bonus depreciation that provided
these providers with billions of dollars
of free tax flow. Um, for example, um,
AT&T had $18 billion in free cash flow
in 2026. Um, and they're expected to get
about 19 billion and 21 billion in the
two years going beyond this. And, um,
you know, so we see similar numbers on
large companies like these cable
operators. So, uh, a lot of free cash
flow to invest in fiber. um great for
the consumers being able to lower their
bills and um great for the also the
profitability of their shareholders on
you know being able to sell all these
other services. So um it seems to fit
right like double to tail right into
kind of our analysis.
Yeah, a a kind of a consistent principle
at the PUC in terms of its, you know,
its oversight of of kind of critical
infrastructure in in communications,
energy, and water. Um, is there's there
the the appropriate like means of
benefit has to be a shared benefit
between the what we call the rateayer or
the customer and the shareholders. And
so the transition from kind of legacy
copper to fiber really presented a a a
sweet spot there that I think facilitate
our ability to negotiate a a really good
proposal between the company and and the
and what we offer for the commission to
review. You although the commission will
will make it decisions you know later
this year in terms of carry last resort.
But on paper, what uh AT&T and the
public advocates office were willing to
agree to was a structured transition
of um kind of legacy, you know, voice
obligations in areas that are
predominantly uh g you know, gigabit
soul gigabit territory. Um you know, you
know, we give or take we have millions
of of households in in the state of
California, but are mostly sle gigabit
under cable. And uh AT&T's commitment
under that structure, you know, will
fully committed would would exceed, you
know, 1 million fiber lines in 10 years.
And so it is it is very much a, you
know, I know they want to build it. I
know the customers benefit from it
existing in and the entry and this data
we were able to produce in January which
is kind of fortuitous timing because we
we didn't really plan it to coincide
with with certain proceedings at that
timing because this took months of uh
work with our academic partners to pull
together. But it really pointed out that
there was a cognizable benefit to the
consumer if they received at least two
gigabit options and fiber being kind of
the main entry of that of that second
choice. The other thing that was, you
know, just to kind of stress the point a
bit was surprising though was to the
extent that fixed wireless broadband um
was just was not moving prices. You
know, so there's one thing to say uh you
people were leaving one service to the
other, but the but the real fundamental
for us was was it making the existing
customers, you know, who were
subscribing to cable in in large parts
um were they receiving the benefits of
competition which should come from
lowering prices in response to
competitive entry and we just we were
unable to detect any meaningful movement
from sub gigabit services was we call
them. You know what's interesting is
when I look at our research um and even
like recon analytics has done some
really good studies and it really one of
the things they u produced here last
fall was showing that the type of you
know your behavior on fiber versus
lesser quality connectivity. So like on
fiber one is 75% of fiber users are
using AI daily and they also are using
these you know largely on laptops or you
know some kind of desktop or you know so
they're doing work from home they're
doing telealth they're doing um online
education you know video game I mean
they're using these very rich media kind
of applications where I run the when you
look down at fix wireless or even cable
fix wireless and um LEO uh like less
than 10% of LEO subscribers use AI daily
and they're most of the LEO providers
are using their cell phone. So it's you
know you're you're you're a different
kind of subscriber when you don't care
about the quality of your broadband
connection or you only have a low
quality connection available to you. And
so that's where you you know I think
where your study kind of zeroed in on
gigabit. You know the other part of this
I think is interesting is you know back
in 2010 right Blair Leven's you know
when he's doing the national broadband
plan broadband was defined as one
megabit right and you know right now we
are deploying 10 gigabit symmetric
networks and this will be the first year
that we're get into volume deployment of
25 gigs networks and so we're going to
see these you know I have five gigs a
metric to my house and I'm paying the
same price as I was paying to the cable
provider. And what the deep dark secret
of cable is they never tell you what the
upstream is. Um right you know my
service was called superfast and I'm
trying to figure out all the fine print
what superfast means but um you know
it's it's when you you're subscribing to
a gigabit service but you have such poor
upstream that I couldn't do um my
teleahalth sessions you know and so you
know that's the thing that doesn't come
out on these that um when you see a
cable and you know what the speed is
they're not talking about symmetric
they're just talking about the down
downstream speeds.
Yeah, I think so. That's an area that I
think we are um we are considering how
to study and kind of break apart uh
specifically
the
use cases and usefulness of the axis.
So, you know, we're we're getting past
the point, you know, with bead coming in
and, you know, California has kind of
parallel grant programs to the federal
system on almost every regard. You we
fund broadband infrastructure and we
also subsidize uh life. We have our own
lifeline program for example and the
use cases or or you know how do you
maintain particular for like the
low-inccome population you know which is
the special emphasis for us um how do we
ensure they're able to use the fullness
of the internet and kind of the fullness
of the opportunities that the internet's
supposed to create and I do think the
you know kind of the advent of AI tools
and kind of the learning opportunities
there and and you look at just what's
happening with video sharing at this
stage Those are massive files. Um, you
know, I get I get frustrated. I I have a
you know, not the best upload speed on
my in my connection here. And, uh, if I
needed to analyze a substantive document
or or something of a, you know, sizable
nature, uploading it to the tool in the
first place just to begin the analysis
is is a drag. I mean, it's it's it's a
it's a it's a delay that then I have to
kind of just go do something else while
I'm waiting for it. And I, you know, I
have a pretty good internet connection.
I I actually am pretty uh satisfied for
the most part. But you know with each
passing year as as the demand cycle
grows and and the applications and the
intensivity of those applications
continue to advance um you know I'm
going to need to keep going up. Uh and
that's something we're trying to you get
a handle on kind of what is like an
essential minimum of service more than
you know I could say with confidence
it's not 10020 up anymore. It's it's
moved past that at this point. Um, yeah,
but how do we how do we be more dynamic
as as regulators to
>> assess whether the community is at a
point where they're really ensuring
everyone has the full benefit of the
internet?
>> Well, I mean, I think AI is such a
gamecher and it's going to disrupt every
model. I mean, even just websites, you
know, you never know who goes to website
anymore, right? You use uh your AI
search and be able to get all the
information you need versus going to
individual websites. the way the
internet's monetized even it's going to
disrupt the monopolies that um Android
and and the iPhone have on the cell
phone market. So it's it's going to be a
big disruptor and I think you know we'll
start seeing quality of connections
become paramount. Um so one thing you
know if I look at your study it's pretty
straightforward. to use a bunch of
university guys. You guys can't, you
know, I think it's intuitively obvious
that you, you know, you're not going to
see any price movement. If uh inferior
service comes to market, why would you
bother changing prices? But if a real
threat like you know you put a
McDonald's across from a Burger King or
a Walgreens across from a Eards or
whatever the you know every you can take
any industry and you put the competition
across you're going to get um stronger
more consumerfriendly pricing. Um but I
did see a blog from a bunch of ACL guys
that kind of weren't too happy with this
study. Um any comments on that or
I
>> mean I think it boils down to um there
is this this I think theory to say
um you know a bunch of low options is
sufficient to consider competition and
then and and why are we complaining when
we're talking about you know when we
obsess of the gigabit tier. Um and I I
guess my my response to that is the
these companies wouldn't be offering a
gigabit service if there wasn't demand
for it.
And um you know I think next month we'll
probably put out more on showing where
the demand is in in terms of the state
in terms of the population but you know
like I said it's about 75% of all uh
people who buy broadband in California
are are purchasing speeds at 300 500 or
gigabit. um you know the market exists
because the demand exists and so to say
we should be focusing on you know I
would say inferior or kind of
yesterday's speeds as a means of
assessing kind of where uh where things
are at and where competition is at where
pricing because that uh really is is
missing you know who are the buyers and
and what are they buying um the future
is is always going to head upwards in
terms of the demand the internet's kind
of demonstrated that for for decades um
you know be I think recognized that in
terms of the priority broadband
project's provisioning of scalability
recognizing we will always need more um
you know and as you pointed out
correctly you know in the age of AI and
kind of these new generation of services
we we can I think we can all agree with
confidence we're going to be moving a
lot more data you know in the next year
than we are even this year and each year
we'll continue to kind of break these
new thresholds one thing I also have
been interested to kind of see is um
it's not so much just fiber entry and it
and its own isolation that creates a
benefit. I also think that is a reason
why cable is rolling out DOC's 4.0 right
which is where they're going to you 10
gigabit and beyond and symmetrical
speeds and essentially replicating what
fiber companies are doing you know now
um they wouldn't be rolling that out
unless that's they recognize that's
where the consumers are going to go uh
at the end of the day. So, I just think
it's it's kind of arguing yesterday's
battles if we if we continue to look at
the FCC standard as a a means of
assessing whether things are in a good
place uh for for consumers at this
stage.
Yeah, it's you know it's really
frustrating with some of the policy
federal policy makers that uh for
example end of last week the farm bill
text came out and uh for broadband you
know for USDA they were suggesting 50 by
and it's just like these guys are
supposed to be protecting farmers not
relegating them to not be able to
leverage you know precision farming and
all the you know when you start to do
digital twins and all the data that's
going to be on farms, you're really
going to try to screw guys over with
things that are beyond a decade ago. I
mean, it's it's crazy. But um
>> yeah and if you look at the
international markets and kind of you
know we should be getting to a point
where the the speed becomes irrelevant
because the infrastructure can scale
consistently in a way that makes me met
measuring speed as the level of
deployment kind of an irrelevant
exercise. Uh we should be migrating
towards latency and um you know the
level of instantaneousness of the
response and you know uptime and things
like that. But yeah, the US is still a
little backwards, I think, on
recognizing how how far behind we can
be. And I think what's what is shocking
sometimes is, you know, you go back to
your state-by-state study, the fact of
the matter is some states have really
already figured this out. Um, I think
I'm always using North Dakota as an
example when I have to talk to um policy
makers in Sacramento who, you know, I
think uh suffer from the perpetual low
expectations of what we could have um to
say, you know, how did a small rural
state with, you know, kind of a fraction
of the funding, a fraction of the
resources of our state, how does it get
to a point where nearly everyone has a
gigabit fiber connection at this point,
right? It's it's policy. It's it's
rights away management. It's it's how we
handle the emphasis of allowing this
infrastructure to build. Um you
California is a big state with lots of
different variables that play into it.
But if we don't set the expectations
correct, the policy the policy and the
outcomes almost never follow and and I
think that's always a a per kind of a
perpetual fight in in this space. But
one but I hope that in our you know not
too distant future we get past. But um
it is it is a point where we need to
move away from lowest common denominator
being good enough simply because we
we'll always come back and have to spend
the money again and again and again
until we finally get it right.
>> Well, that's the thing we've seen with
any funding program uh broadband subsidy
is anytime you don't invest in fiber
you're funding those same locations over
and over again. you know whether it's
one megabit or four by one or 10 by one
or 253 or 100 by 20 or you know on on
versus just do it once. I mean that's
but you know it's the life we live here
is to make room for uh you know all
constituents. But listen, um, we're out
of time, Ernie, but I really appreciate,
uh, I always enjoy every, you know,
everything that you work on and, uh, I
appreciate the great work that you and
your colleagues at California PC are
doing to advance broadband in your state
and, uh, so thank you for that and
thanks for sharing your report.
>> Come on and and and thank you for the
opportunity to present to your audience.
>> Well, I want to thank everybody for
joining us today. look forward to
getting back together next Wednesday
with one of my favorite people um the
Fiber Broadband Association's former
chairman and our current treasurer Jimmy
Todd who is the CEO of NEXTE. He's going
to discuss getting a front row seat to
the telecom evolution 75 years in the
making. So that's going to be fun. Look
forward to seeing you next Wednesday.
Thanks everyone and u Ernie, we'll see
you soon.